Curriculum Vitae - Sunitha Varghese

Personal Information

Name Dr Sunitha Varghese Date of Birth 6th November 1977

Nationality Indian

Telephone +91 9721150369

Email address drsunithavarghese@gmail.com,sunitha.varghese@eha-health.org

Primary affiliation

Project Director and Medical consultant-Fatehpur, Community health and development department, Emmanuel Hospital Association, New delhi- India

Education

University: Tamil Nadu Dr. MGR Medical University 1996-2001, 2005-2008.

Degrees:

MBBS graduated in 2001, Christian Medical College, Vellore Tamil Nadu, India

MD- Community Health, graduated in 2008, Christian Medical College, Vellore

Positions and employment

- 2001-02 House Surgeoncy at Christian Medical College, Vellore.
- 2002-04 CSI Mission Hospital, Codacal, Kerala, India as Resident Medical Officer
- 2005-08 Post Graduate Registrarship (2005-2008) In Community Medicine
- 2008-2014 Medical Consultant with additional responsibilities of Community health Program Directorship at Broadwell Christian Hospital, Fatehpur, Uttar Pradesh- A unit of Emmanuel Hospital Association.
- 2014 till present- Community health Program Director, Fatehpur with additional roles of Medical consultant at Broadwell Christian hospital
- 2014 till present-Regional Co-coordinator of North central region Projects of Emmanuel Hospital Association.
- 2015 till present-EHA Thematic director for Reproductive and Maternal health programs
- 2017 till present, in addition to the above, EHA Community Health Deputy Director

Community health experience in detail_Community health program director –Broadwell Christian Hospital, Fatehpur, UP for the following projects/ Programs till date-

- 2008-12: Teliyani block Community Health and development project-In conjunction with National Rural Health Mission, Capacity building of the ASHA worker(community based health worker) and development of the Village Health and sanitation committees in 55 villages of Teliyani block, Fatehpur district, Uttar Pradesh(Funded by TEAR Australia)
- 2008-10 :CHASINI project- sensitisation and mobilisation of the public on Gender issues and HIV- AIDS implemented in Teliyani block of Fatehpur district (funded by CHRISTIAN AID)

- 2008-10 :URBAN Fatehpur Project Health and Development of four Urban slums in the Fatehpur Municipality and empowerment through Self help groups and Resident welfare associations (funded by TEAR Australia)
- 2010-14 RSBY –UNDP project implementation in Fatehpur District-A supplementary venture to the Rastrya Swasthya Bhima Yojana Health insurance scheme for the Below Poverty line families by the Government of India, which focuses on access, enrollment and utilization of this scheme by the entitled beneficiaries in the district
- 2011-14: URBAN Fatehpur Project -Health and Development of additional 15 Urban slums by processes of community organization and creating health care demand(funded by TEAR Australia)
- 2011-17: AXSHYA(GFATM round 9 recipient) through the IUTLD 2011and ongoing program
 implementation of ACSM activities towards Tuberculosis awareness with the RNTCP Fatehpur
 district.
- 2011-17 : ICTC program at Broadwell Christian hospital, Fatehpur (2011 and ongoing) with UPSACS, Lucknow.
- 2012-17 : Medical Director of Palliative care program- Broadwell Christian hospital

Community health project implementation evaluations conducted on behalf of development program funding agencies-

- Bissamcuttack Tribal project MITRA evaluation May 2007 called by CHAD, CMC Vellore.
- Secondary evaluator for the mid-term Evaluation of Kacchwa Christian Hospital Community health and Development Project, Uttar Pradesh called by TEAR UK in October 2011 with Public health consultant Dr. Daisy Dharamraj.
- Secondary evaluator for the End line evaluation of Rural Project Fatehpur October 2012 called by TEAR AU with Public Health consultant Ms. Blessina Kumar.
- Secondary evaluator for the end line evaluation of Urban health project December 2013 called by TEAR AU with consultant Ms. Rekha Abraham
- Primary evaluator of the NACO- Harm reduction project among IV drug users in the Indo Nepal border, Raxaul, Bihar, led by EHA, India
- Primary evaluator of the Urban health project by Duncan hospital, Bihar called by EHA, India
- Secondary evaluator of the SHARE project of Ted Lankaster in Uttar Pradesh called by EHA, India

Other experiences, awards and memberships

Awards

- 2008- Rangarajan Gold medal in Community Medicine, Christian Medical College, Vellore, For excellence in MD Community Medicine.
- 2012-Award for best Project implementation- Emmanuel Hospital Association
- 2017-Award for best Financial management of Projects- Emmanuel Hospital Association
- Best female western vocalist Christian Medical College annual music fest, 1997

Memberships and governance roles

- 2008 -2017 Member of Unit management Committee, Broadwell Christian Hospital
- 2012-17 Member of District health Forum, Fatehpur District, Uttar Pradesh representing Private medical sector
- 2012-15 Member of the District Tuberculosis control forum, representing the Medical Fraternity.

- 2014-17 Presiding officer of Internal Complaints Committee, Broadwell Christian Hospital
- 2014-17 Member of the Management of SHARE project management Committee, Bijnor District, Uttar Pradesh
- 2016-17 Implementation officer of the Gender policy of Emmanuel Hospital Association.

Publications

- 1. Natl Med J India 2013;26:142–6 Domestic violence as a risk factor for infant and child mortality: A community-based case–control study from southern India, S. Varghese, J. Prasad, K.S Jacob
- 2. Safar Magazine- Monsoon edition 2013- Key article- Social determinants of health, S. Varghese (non Peer-reviewed article)
- 3. MFC bulletin/December 2016 February 2017 :373-374:19-20 K Mathias- Community based screening for Oral cancer in Fatehpur District, Uttar Pradesh

Presentations

Poster presentation, Role of Self Help Groups in promotion of health, -International Conference on Urban Health 2010 at the New York Academy of Medicine, New York, USA

Unpublished studies

- 1. A study of the knowledge, attitude and practice of smoking among new fathers. (January-March 2006) Co-investigator
- 2. The evaluation of a new Socio-economic scoring scale developed in Lucknow. (April-June 2006) Coinvestigator
- 3. A case control study to assess the qualities of Health Insurance acceptors in Kavanur. (July September 2006) Co-investigator
 - 4. Quality of care for TB-HIV –A rights based approach. (October- December 2006) Co-investigator
 - 5. Prevalence of alcohol use among college students. (January-March 2007) Co-investigator
 - 6. Incidence of falls among the elderly in Kaniyambadi block. (April-June 2007) Co-investigator
- 7. Qualities of care for Rh Negative mothers and a study of the outcomes of those pregnancies- An Audit. (July –September 2007) Co-investigator
- 8. Knowledge, attitude and practice of spacing methods for family planning among new mothers (October- December 2007) Co-investigator.
- 9. Prevalence of Diabetes among Patients with cataracts conducted from July- December 2010, with Wheaton University intern- Ms.Heather Grose.- primary investigator
- 10. Prevalence of Alcoholism among urban families in Fatehpur town, Uttar Pradesh November 2010 with Cambridge university Research Intern Dr. Hamish Findlay-primary investigator

Relevant course attended

- 1. Research Methodology October 2005 Organized by the Clinical Epidemiology Unit, CMC Vellore
- 2. Basic Epidemiology August 2006 Organized by the Epidemiology Research Centre, Dept of Community Medicine, CMC Vellore
- 3. Basics of Computers in Epidemiological studies August 2006 Organized by the Computer Cell, Dept of Community Medicine, CMC Vellore.
- 4. Continuing Medical Education in Community Psychiatry 2007 Organized by Dept. Of Continued Medical Education and Dept. of Psychiatry, CMC Vellore.
- 5. Basics of Health Economics –August 2007 Organized by the Dept of Community Medicine, CMC Vellore.
- 6. Clinical Trials 2008 Organized by the Epidemiology Research Centre, Dept of Community Medicine, CMC Vellore.
- 7. Course on Case control studies 2008 Organized by the Epidemiology Research Centre, Dept of Community Medicine, CMC Vellore.

Personal Statement

I have the implementation experience, leadership, training, and motivation necessary to successfully carry out the proposed PhD studies. I have a broad background in Medicine& Surgery, with specific training and expertise in Public health, particularly health and development issues of vulnerable populations. For the past ten years I have been working in a remote rural and underprivileged region of North India, Fatehpur as a clinician and additionally Community health program director. I have been predominantly clinically engaged, our institution being the only reliable medical care for a target population of 2600,000 people. This means that I have stretched myself to do Obstetrics, Surgery, Paediatrics, General Medicine and continue responsibility for health and development projects, being one of only two doctors posted to this unit, the other being my husband, while continuing with family responsibilities. Though I have training in Research and epidemiology, I have been limited in the practice and publishing of research projects for several years, due to the urgency of clinical medicine and lack of health personnel in remote regions of India. However the richness of clinical experience has helped me see and understand and study diseases of poverty. Therefore I find myself highly motivated to carry out research and am seeking opportunities to carry out systematic research.

I have successfully administered several health and development projects over the years, and have won awards. I understand the importance of leadership, team work, co-ordination and communication in Project implementation. I am committed to more research and documentation emphasis over the coming years.